<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source>PubMed</source><date>20220101</date><key>BioC.key</key><document><id>34460882</id><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>0</offset><text>MEN1 mutations mediate clinical resistance to menin inhibition</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>63</offset><text>Chromatin-binding proteins are critical regulators of cell state in haematopoiesis  1, 2  . Acute leukaemias driven by rearrangement of the mixed lineage leukaemia 1 gene (KMT2Ar) or mutation of the nucleophosmin gene (NPM1) require the chromatin adapter protein menin, encoded by the MEN1 gene, to sustain aberrant leukaemogenic gene expression programs  [3] [4] [5]  . In a phase 1 first-in-human clinical trial, the menin inhibitor revumenib, which is designed to disrupt the menin-MLL1 interaction, induced clinical responses in patients with leukaemia with KMT2Ar or mutated NPM1 (ref.  6  ). Here we identified somatic mutations in MEN1 at the revumenib-menin interface in patients with acquired resistance to menin inhibition. Consistent with the genetic data in patients, inhibitor-menin interface mutations represent a conserved mechanism of therapeutic resistance in xenograft models and in an unbiased base-editor screen. These mutants attenuate drug-target binding by generating structural perturbations that impact small-molecule binding but not the interaction with the natural ligand MLL1, and prevent inhibitor-induced eviction of menin and MLL1 from chromatin. To our knowledge, this study is the first to demonstrate that a chromatin-targeting therapeutic drug exerts sufficient selection pressure in patients to drive the evolution of escape mutants that lead to sustained chromatin occupancy, suggesting a common mechanism of therapeutic resistance. Menin is a chromatin adaptor protein that is critical for the formation and stability of highly conserved multiprotein complexes on chromatin, including MLL1 (also known as KMT2A) and MLL2 (also known as KMT2B) histone methyltransferase complexes and the JUND transcription factor complex 4,7,8 . Menin is critical for the development and maintenance of acute leukaemias driven by KMT2Ar or NPM1 mutations  3, 5  . A series of small-molecule inhibitors that disrupt the menin-MLL1 protein-protein interaction have been developed 9-14 and demonstrate potent activity in preclinical models, including the ability to eradicate disease  5, 10, 14  . On the basis of this, several menin inhibitors recently entered phase 1 clinical trials (NCT04065399, NCT04067336, NCT04811560, NCT05388903, NCT04988555 and NCT05153330). The menin inhibitor revumenib (also known as SNDX-5613) has been reported to be safe and effective in patients with relapsed or refractory acute leukaemia with an KMT2Ar or NPM1 mutation. In the ongoing phase 1/2 first-in-human study (AUGMENT-101) of revumenib, patients with KMT2Ar or NPM1c-mutant leukaemia had an overall response rate of 53%, with 30% of treated patients achieving a complete remission or complete remission with partial haematological recovery 6 . Here we identified and characterized somatic mutations within the MEN1 gene that arise during menin inhibitor treatment and mediate therapeutic resistance in model systems and in patients enrolled in the AUGMENT-101 trial (NCT04065399).  MEN1 mutations in resistant leukaemias Despite significant single-agent activity of revumenib in a heavily pretreated patient population with KMT2Ar and NPM1-mutant leukaemia, we identified patients who were treated on the AUGMENT-101 phase 1 study and subsequently developed acquired resistance following an</text><annotation id="0"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="456" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="1"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="596" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="2"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="742" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="3"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="833" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="4"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="1382" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="5"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="2452" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="6"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="2572" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="7"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="2612" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="8"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="2716" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="9"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="2998" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="10"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="3175" length="7"/><text>patient</text></annotation><annotation id="11"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="3247" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>3367</offset><text>initial response (Fig.  1a ). Patients 1 and 4 with relapsed KMT2Ar acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) achieved morphological leukaemia-free states after one cycle of treatment, followed by relapse despite continued exposure to the study drug. Patient 2 with NPM1-mutant AML had a reduction in circulating blast counts after two cycles of revumenib followed by disease progression, whereas patient 3 with KMT2Ar AML achieved a complete remission with incomplete count recovery and then progressed despite continued treatment with the menin inhibitor (Fig.  1a ). Next-generation targeted sequencing of bone marrow specimens from these patients at diagnosis revealed a largely stable landscape of well-characterized leukaemia drivers, but somatic mutations within the MEN1 gene were detected at time of relapse on revumenib (Extended Data Fig.  1a-c ). In three out of four patients, the M327 residue was affected (M327V or M327I), and T349M, G331R and S160T were detected in each one of the three patients at the end of treatment, respectively (Fig.  1a ). Mutation allele frequencies ranged from 5.9% to 28.2% (Extended Data Fig.  1a-c ), owing to expected dilution effects from normal leukocytes. To quantitatively assess the frequency of these novel somatic mutations within the population of patients with KMT2Ar and the NPM1 mutation who had been exposed to revumenib, we performed droplet digital PCR (ddPCR) for MEN1  M327V  , MEN1  M327I  , MEN1  G331R  , MEN1  G331D  and MEN1 T349M on DNA samples collected during the AUGMENT-101 trial at different study centres. We identified 31 patients, inclusive of responders and non-responders, who were treated with revumenib for more than two cycles of treatment (more than 56 days) and had DNA material available for analysis. Among these patients, 12 individuals (38.7%) carried one or more MEN1 mutations (Fig.  1b  and Extended Data Fig.  1d ). Of note, these mutations were not detected in the pretreatment samples by ddPCR, suggesting that they were either not present or present in very low abundance until menin inhibition established a selective fitness advantage (Fig.  1c ). Due to the sensitivity of the ddPCR assay, the patients found to harbor MEN1 mutations were not necessarily in overt relapse at time of detection. Longitudinal assessment of the detected mutations in single patients confirmed clonal outgrowth during drug treatment and suggested that selection for MEN1-mutant leukaemia cells occurs after approximately two cycles of therapy (Fig.  1d  and Extended Data Fig.  1e ). In parallel, we conducted a preclinical study in which we treated five different patient-derived xenografts (PDXs) derived from patients with AML (four with KMT2Ar and one with NPM1) with the menin inhibitor VTP-50469, which is a close analogue of revumenib that binds similarly to menin  14  . We assessed long-term survival for up to 400 days after initiation of treatment. Out of 45 animals treated with the drug, 22 xenografted mice (from all five PDX models) relapsed during drug exposure or after treatment cessation or had human leukaemia cells detected in the bone marrow at the end of treatment without overt manifestations of disease. Targeted DNA sequencing and/or ddPCR were performed on 33 specimens (11 untreated and all 22 relapsed animals). MEN1 mutations were identified in 15 (68%) of those relapsed samples from 4 PDX models (Fig.  1e -g and Supplementary Table  2 ). MEN1 M327V , MEN1 M327I , MEN1 G331R , MEN1 G331D , MEN1 T349M and MEN1 S160C mutations were detected, demonstrating high recurrence and an exceptional predictive value of the PDX model system. In PDX1 (MLL::AF6) and PDX2 (NPM1), we observed relapse in single animals, whereas disease was eradicated in a large proportion of the cohort (Fig.  1e, f ). The MEN1 mutations identified in those animals were diverse and included M327I, M327V, G331D and T349M and arose after a relatively long period of drug exposure, suggesting that de novo mutations were acquired during treatment. By contrast, all menin inhibitor-treated recipients engrafted with sample PDX3 (MLL::AF10) relapsed after about 2 months of continuous drug treatment (Fig.  1g  and Extended Data Fig.  2a-c ). All mice possessed T349M mutations, possibly reflecting the selection of a pre-existent ultra-low-frequency variant that could not be detected pre-therapy in bone marrow isolates (Fig.  1g , Extended Data Fig.  2d  and Supplementary Table  2 ). In PDX4 (MLL::AF9, AML) resistance developed in four of nine animals without MEN1 mutations or other newly acquired genetic drivers detectable, indicating that adaptation and non-genetic processes may also lead to menin inhibitor resistance in individual cases. Similarly, disease persistence could be detected in four of nine VTP-50469-treated animals in PDX5 (MLL::AF9, AML), whereas in only one of these animals, a menin mutation (T349M) could be detected. In summary, we identified recurrent somatic mutations within the MEN1 gene that affect the M327, G331, T349 and S160 residues of menin in patients and PDX models who relapsed on menin inhibitor treatment. These mutations are distinct from known variants that disrupt the tumour suppressive function of menin in MEN1 syndrome and none has been previously reported  15  . To gain an unbiased view on the spectrum of point mutations that may cause resistance to menin inhibitors, we conducted a MEN1-focused CRISPR-Cas9 base-editor screen in MOLM13 (MLL::AF9) and MV4;11 (MLL::AF4) cells. A library of 518 single guide RNAs targeting all MEN1 exons and flanking untranslated regions was designed and expressed along with a base-editor system to facilitate C→T base editing in proximity to the single guide RNA-binding sites  16  . Subsequently, cells were exposed to VTP-50469 or DMSO for 12 days and guide barcodes were counted by next-generation sequencing to identify editing sites that confer resistance to drug treatment (Extended Data Fig.  3a ). Using this approach, base editing affecting the majority of amino acids within menin could be achieved. The T349, G331 and S160 residues were predicted as candidate drivers of menin inhibitor resistance in the screen (Fig.  2a , Extended Data Fig.  3b  and Supplementary Table  3 ), but the M327 residue was not amenable to a base edit due to the lack of a PAM sequence in this specific region. The X-ray co-crystal structure of revumenib bound to menin revealed that residues M327, G331 and T349 are located in close proximity to the W346 residue (Fig.  2b , Extended Data Fig.  3c ,e and Supplementary Table  10 ). There is a strong hydrogen bond between the sulfonamide oxygen of revumenib and the indole N-H of W346 that contributes to inhibitor binding. This interaction was previously observed for the related inhibitor VTP-50469 (ref.  14  ). In addition, we observed a hydrogen bond between the sulfonamide nitrogen of revumenib and the backbone ketone oxygen of M327. The key amino acids affected by MEN1 mutations (M327, G331 and T349) are located around the W346 residue and do not overlap with the binding interface of MLL1 (Extended Data Fig.  3d, e ), which suggests that they probably perturb the distal revumenib sulfonamide interaction. Co-crystallography of revumenib with the menin(M327I) mutant confirmed this effect. As seen in the overlay of the wild-type (WT) and mutant menin revumenib structures (Fig.  2b ), the branching methyl group of I327 projects towards the cyclohexyl ring of revumenib. The resulting steric clash displaces revumenib, leading to disruption of the hydrogen bonds with W346, as well as with M327, reducing the binding affinity of the inhibitor while leaving the other interactions of the molecule with menin largely unchanged. In parallel, we used computational methods to assess dynamic structural changes in menin incorporating MEN1 T349M , MEN1 G331D , MEN1 G331R , MEN1  M327I  and MEN1 M327V for the revumenib-menin interface, using the Folding@home distributed computing platform  17  . We launched all-atom molecular dynamics simulations of WT menin and individual mutant forms in both the presence and the absence of revumenib (Extended Data Fig.  4a-d ), collecting an aggregate of 5.469 ms of simulation. Through a combination of deep learning methods  18  and Markov state models  19  , we predicted reductions in protein-ligand contacts between menin and revumenib, perturbing the binding mode and decreasing affinity. Consistent with the structural and computational results, competitive MLL1 fluorescence polarization binding assays  20  showed that the M327I and T349M mutants increased the half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC 50 ) values of revumenib for MLL displacement by 51-fold and 111-fold compared with WT menin (Fig.  2c  and Extended Data Fig.  5a-c ). The reduced affinity seen in the fluorescence polarization binding assay was consistent with a more than 30-fold increase in the dissociation off rate of revumenib from M327I versus WT menin (Extended Data Fig.  5b ) and more than 50-fold change in mutant binding affinities (K d ) determined by isothermal titration calorimetry (Extended Data Fig.  5c ). Similarly, binding of MI3454, a structural analogue of KO-539, and DS-25, a potent compound from the Daiichi Sankyo series  21  , were also severely affected by M327I, suggesting that menin inhibitor resistance at this site exhibits a broad class effect (Fig.  2c ). Bindings of MI3454 and DS-25 were differentially affected by the M327I and T349M mutation, respectively (Fig.  2c ). Moreover, this mutant effect is not specific to the menin-MLL1 interaction, as the ability of the menin inhibitor to block menin-MLL2 binding was similarly affected by M327I and T349M mutations (Extended Data Fig.  5d, e ). The ability of the mutants to bind to the MLL1 peptide remained largely intact, although a subtle decrease in binding affinity was observed for T349M-mutant menin (Fig.  2d ). Together, we independently reproduced the narrow spectrum of MEN1-hotspot mutations observed in patients and PDX by using an unbiased in vitro screening approach. Furthermore, we mapped these residues to an area of the binding pocket that is crucial for stabilizing binding of the menin inhibitor molecules but is dispensable for MLL1 binding. We next assessed whether the mutations conferred resistance to menin inhibitor treatment in vitro. We expressed MEN1 M327I , MEN1 G331R and MEN1 T349M mutants as well as a WT menin complementary DNA in MOLM13 (MLL::AF9), MV4;11 (MLL::AF4) and OCI-AML3 (NPM1-mutant) cells using a lentiviral vector system. Dose-response assays performed by counting the number of viable cells after 10 days of drug treatment demonstrated a robust decrease in revumenib sensitivity in both KMT2Ar and NPM1-mutant cells expressing these mutations (Fig.  3a, b  and Extended Data Fig.  6a-c,f ). Moreover, the induction of myeloid differentiation upon menin inhibitor treatment was impaired (Extended Data Fig.  6d, e ). Of note, this resistance phenotype could similarly be observed when cells were treated with the structurally unrelated menin inhibitor MI3454 (Extended Data Fig.  6f ). The degree of drug resistance observed using this system may be dependent on the expression level of each construct (Extended Data Fig.  6g, h ). To overcome the limitations of ectopic expression, we utilized CRISPR-Cas9 in conjunction with a homology directed repair template to edit M327I or T349M mutations into the endogenous MEN1-coding sequence of MV4;11 and OCI-AML3 cells (Fig.  3c ). After nucleofection, M327I-edited or unedited bulk populations of cells were exposed to 50 nM of revumenib and cell counts were monitored over the course of 1 month (Fig.  3d ). Unedited MV4;11 and OCI-AML3 cells stopped dividing shortly after exposure to the menin inhibitor, whereas CRISPR-Cas9-edited cells continued growing beyond 28 days, which was accompanied by positive selection for the M327I mutation (Fig.  3e ), providing in vitro support for the concept of inhibitor-driven clonal selection by this mutation. After screening of single-cell clones, we established cell lines with M327I and T349M mutations (Extended Data Fig.  7a ). MEN1 M327I/M327I MV4;11 cells did not respond to revumenib at physiologically relevant doses with IC 50 values shifting from the low nanomolar range to over 1 μM when the mutation was present (Fig.  3f  and Extended Data Fig.  7b ). MEN1 M327I/WT cell lines retained some sensitivity to menin inhibition; however, IC 50 values were increased by 16-fold compared with MEN1 WT cells (Fig.  3f ). Consistent with the findings from our binding assays, we observed reduced sensitivity to revumenib, MI3454 and the Daiichi Sankyo compounds in M327I-mutant and T349M-mutant MV4;11 and OCI-AML3 cells (Fig.  3g, h  and Extended Data Fig.  7c-e ). Of note, the observation that MI3454 binding in the fluorescence polarization assay was less affected by   Outstanding hits are marked in red, and targeted amino acid residues are labelled. The red dotted line indicates a CRISPR score of 1, above which hits may be considered significant. The blue bar highlights the hotspot region in which most menin mutations are located. b, Structure alignment between the co-crystal structure of revumenib bound to M327I-mutant menin (PDB: 8E90) and revumenib bound to WT menin (PDB: 7UJ4). Revumenib is coloured in yellow in WT menin and magenta in the M327-mutant co-crystal structure. The magenta dashed lines indicate large distances, incapable of hydrogen bond interactions, between revumenib in the M327I mutant and the WT menin protein, and are in contrast to the hydrogen bond between W346 and revumenib in the WT menin (highlighted with the black dashed line). c, Fluorescence polarization assay measuring dose-dependent displacement of an MLL1 peptide from WT, M327I-mutant and T349M-mutant menin under treatment with revumenib (left), MI3454 (middle) or DS-25 (right), which is a compound from the Daiichi Sankyo menin inhibitor series. Data are presented as a fraction bound of three independent replicates (n = 3). Each data point represents the mean ± s.d. K i , inhibition constant. d, Fluorescence polarization assay probing the binding affinity of a MLL1 peptide to WT, M327I-mutant and T349M-mutant menin. Data are presented as a fraction bound of three independent replicates (n = 3). Each data point represents the mean ± s.d. T349M was reflected in the dose-response curves (Fig.  3h  and Extended Data Fig.  7e ). We further found that cells expressing MEN1 M327I were also resistant to another menin inhibitor, M-89, and we confirmed that the more N-terminal-located S160C mutation conferred a similar degree of revumenib resistance (Extended Data Fig.  7f, g ). To answer the question whether the presence of recurrent MEN1 mutations may impact the fitness of leukaemia cells in the absence of a menin inhibitor, we performed a cell competition assay (Extended Data Fig.  7h ). As expected, revumenib exposure led to a rapid selection of M327I-mutant and T349M-mutant cells, whereas the chimerism between mutant and non-mutant cells decreased under DMSO treatment (Extended Data Fig.  7h ). This effect was particularly pronounced for T349M-mutant cells and only subtle when M327I was present, corresponding to the MLL1-binding assay (Fig.  2f ). In summary, we demonstrated that endogenous or exogenous expression of recurrent MEN1 mutants in KMT2Ar or NPM1-mutant AML cell lines is sufficient to induce drug resistance to a panel of currently available menin inhibitors. We next investigated whether mutations that confer menin inhibitor resistance attenuate the changes in chromatin and gene expression seen with inhibition of the menin-MLL1 interaction in MEN1 WT leukaemia cells. Chromatin immunoprecipitation followed by sequencing (ChIP-seq) was performed after treatment of the MV4;11 MEN1 M327I/M327I and WT control cell lines with revumenib to assess genome-wide chromatin occupancy of menin and MLL1 (Fig.  4a ). As expected, treatment of MEN1 WT cells led to near-complete and global displacement of menin from chromatin with exposure to as little as 100 nM of revumenib. By contrast, M327I-mutant cells retained menin on chromatin and only showed a partial decrease in menin chromatin occupancy even when exposed to 5 μM of revumenib (Fig.  4a, b ). Consequently, inhibitor-induced MLL eviction from key target loci, including MEIS1, was largely abrogated in M327I-mutant MV4;11 cells (Fig.  4c  and Extended Data Fig.  8a ). Consistent with these findings in the MLL::AF4-rearranged MV4;11 cells, displacement of menin from chromatin was blunted in both M327I-mutant and NPM1-mutant OCI-AML3 cells (Extended Data Fig.  8b-d ). Furthermore, treatment of mice that were engrafted with the T349M-mutant PDX3 failed to displace menin from chromatin after oral menin inhibitor treatment in vivo (Extended Data Fig.  8e, f ). The profound loss of MLL1 from promoters with the highest degree of menin displacement (more than 80%) was blunted in T349M-mutant cells (Extended Data Fig.  8g, h ). To delineate the consequences of the altered chromatin-binding dynamics of menin and MLL1 under revumenib treatment, we performed RNA sequencing in MEN1-mutant MV4;11 cells and PDX3 samples. In line with our observations on chromatin, MEN1 M327I -mutant MV4;11 cells showed a high degree of resistance to revumenib-mediated changes in gene expression (Fig.  4d ). Specifically, the repression of canonical menin-MLL1 target genes as well as the induction of gene programs that are associated with myeloid differentiation were largely abrogated in M327I-mutant cells and only a partial response could be observed under treatment with 5 μM of revumenib (Fig.  4h  and Extended Data Fig.  9a, b ). Of note, these effects on gene expression were consistent between the KMT2Ar MV4;11 and the NPM1-mutant OCI-AML3 cells (Extended Data Fig.  10a, b ). Likewise, treatment of mice engrafted with T349M-mutant PDX3 failed to sufficiently repress menin-MLL target genes or induce differentiation-associated gene signatures in human leukaemia cells as compared with mice engrafted with isogenic MEN1 WT cells in response to menin inhibition (Fig.  4e ). Quantitative real-time PCR analysis in leukaemia cells from the NPM1-mutant PDX2 (MEN1 T349M versus WT) showed the same phenomenon (Extended Data Fig.  10c ). The re-engagement of this canonical menin-MLL1-driven gene expression program appears to distinguish MEN1-mutant cases from those that develop resistance in the absence of these mutations. We performed RNA sequencing studies of matched relapse versus pretreatment samples from a patient and PDX4 who had developed menin inhibitor resistance without MEN1 mutations and found significant transcriptional reprogramming (Extended Data Fig.  10d-f ). In contrast to MEN1-mutant cases, these resistant leukaemias had decreased expression of key MLL-target genes (including MEIS1 and HOX genes) and increased expression of myeloid differentiation genes. This suggests the existence of alternative non-genetic mechanisms of resistance that establish a state that is tolerant of an attenuated menin-MLL1 gene expression program. Overall, in both KMT2Ar and NPM1-mutant model systems, we demonstrated that MEN1 resistance mutations prevent menin inhibitor-induced displacement of the menin-MLL1 protein complex from chromatin at critical target genes, which consequently abrogate gene expression changes that are required to terminate leukaemic self-renewal and induce myeloid differentiation. We report that somatic mutations in MEN1 that confer resistance to menin inhibitor treatment are frequently acquired in KMT2Ar and NPM1 leukaemia cells in patients and in preclinical PDX models of disease. These mutations lead to recurrent changes in amino acid residues M327, G331, T349 and S160 and induce drug resistance to structurally distinct classes of menin inhibitors, some of which, including revumenib, have recently entered early-phase clinical trials. The amino acids G331, T349 and S160 were also identified as putative targets for resistance development in a base-editor screen of the MEN1 gene, strengthening the confidence in the predictive value of those experimental systems. These novel MEN1 mutations decrease the affinity of the menin-inhibitor interaction, preventing drug-induced displacement of the menin-MLL1 complex from chromatin and thereby abrogating critical gene expression changes. The affected amino acids are essential for small-molecule binding, but not for MLL1 association with menin, which allows for continued oncogenic activity of the menin-MLL1 complex on chromatin. Most importantly, the discovery of acquired mutations in menin validates the menin-MLL1 interaction as a key oncogenic driver in patients with AML harbouring KMT2Ar or NPM1 mutations and, as such, represents a promising therapeutic target. However, the observation that these mutations confer resistance across multiple menin inhibitors suggests that next-generation inhibitors will be required to circumvent this common mechanism of resistance. Structure-guided drug design to derive second-generation compounds that effectively block MLL1 binding while avoiding interactions with the residues affected by acquired MEN1 mutations may be a feasible strategy to overcome acquired resistance to first-generation menin inhibitors. Given these findings, prospective monitoring of MEN1 mutation status should be considered in patients receiving menin inhibitor therapy, particularly for patients with delayed or incomplete responses, to inform treatment decision-making. To our knowledge, this is the first report of clinically occurring somatic mutations that mediate acquired resistance to small molecules targeting chromatin-binding protein complexes. These data support chromatin complexes and epigenetic mechanisms as critical therapeutic targets in cancer but also suggest that a common mechanism of resistance to therapies targeting these complexes may result from acquired mutagenesis of essential, non-driver epigenetic regulators. Any methods, additional references, Nature Portfolio reporting summaries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, acknowledgements, peer review information; details of author contributions and competing interests; and statements of data and code availability are available at  https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-05755-9 . The human participants who are part of this report were enrolled at the Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center (MSKCC) or the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute (DFCI) in the AUGMENT-101 trial, a phase 1/2, open-label, dose-escalation and dose-expansion cohort study of revumenib in patients with relapsed/refractory leukaemias, including those with KMT2Ar or NPM1c mutation. Additional patient specimens were obtained from the centralized sample bank of Syndax pharmaceuticals. Patients provided oral and written consent to participate in the clinical trial and the sample banking and sequencing program at the MSKCC or the DFCI (IRB 19-448 and 06-107). Assessments of clinical response with bone marrow biopsies and peripheral blood assessment were performed monthly. Approval was obtained from the Institutional Review Board at each institution participating in these clinical trials. Additional consent was obtained from participants at the MSKCC with analyses performed on the institutional biobanking protocol approved by the Institutional Review Board. Patient biospecimens were anonymized by creating unique identifiers with no associated protected health information and keeping the key on a password-protected server. Data collection and research were performed in compliance with all relevant ethical regulations for human research participants. For the assessment of long-term responses and the characterization of drug resistance in the xenograft model system, we used six different PDX models of AML (five for KMT2Ar and one for the NPM1-mutant) that were previously established and characterized in the Center for Pediatric Cancer Therapeutics (CPCT) at the DFCI. Studies were conducted in female NOD.Cg-Prkdc scid Il2rg tm1Wjl /SzJ (NSG) mice ( Jackson Laboratory) 7-9 weeks of age. Cohorts of animals (under long-term treatment with menin inhibitor or control) consisted of 7-10 animals. The sample size of in vivo experiments was based on previous experimental data from preclinical trials using the menin inhibitor. Animals in preclinical trial cohorts were randomly assigned to groups that were treated with the menin inhibitor. Patients were not randomized against a control cohort, as the first-in-human phase 1/2 trial (AUGMENT-101) was not designed and approved as a randomized trial. Investigators on the clinical trial were not blinded as the design of AUGMENT-101 was not designed and approved as a single-blinded or double-blinded trial. Also during preclinical trials, investigators were not blinded. Detailed information on each graft is provided in Supplementary Table  2 . In vivo experiments were performed at the DFCI under the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) protocol #16-021. NOG-mice (Taconic, 10-14 weeks of age) were injected with 250,000 cryo-preserved leukaemia cells of each graft without previous conditioning, and engraftment was monitored in the peripheral blood by detecting the chimerism between human CD45 (PE; clone: HI30, BioLegend; 1:100 for staining) and mouse CD45 (APC-Cy7; clone: 30-F11, BioLegend; 1:100 for staining) using flow cytometry every 3-4 weeks (LSRFortessa, BD Biosciences). When human cells were consistently detectable in all mice of a given graft, oral treatment with VTP-50469 was initiated (0.03% drug-supplemented rodent diet; drug supplied by Syndax Pharmaceuticals; diet produced by ENVIGO). Oral treatment was given for 4 weeks or until no leukaemia cells were detectable anymore in the peripheral blood of mice. After discontinuation, mice were closely monitored by peripheral blood chimerism and treatment was reinitiated upon relapse. Animals that reached the study end point were euthanized using CO 2 inhalation and subsequent cervical dislocation. Tibias, femurs, iliac crests and lumbar vertebrates were cleaned using TX329 cotton wipes (Texwipe) and crushed using mortar and pestle to extract bone marrow cells. Spleen cells were extracted by straining the organ through a 40-μM nylon cell filter (FALCON). The human leukaemia cell burden in the blood, spleen and bone marrow was measured by detecting the chimerism between human CD45 (PE; clone: HI30, BioLegend) and mouse CD45 (APC-Cy7; clone: 30-F11, BioLegend; 1:100 for staining), and the differentiation status of human cells was assessed using anti-CD13 (PerCp-Cy5.5; clone: WM-15, BioLegend; 1:100 for staining), anti-CD14 (PE-Cy7; clone: M5E2, BioLegend; 1:100 for staining) and anti-CD11b (FITC; clone: IRCF44, BioLegend; 1:100 for staining). Targeted DNA sequencing of patient and PDX material Diagnostic bone marrow aspirates were collected from patients before enrolment on the trial and at the time of relapse. Mononuclear cells were isolated via Ficoll gradient centrifugation and genomic DNA was extracted before Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments-approved targeted sequencing was performed (MSKCC-IMPACT). Bone marrow from PDX (at relapse on or after VTP-50469 treatment or treatment naive as control) was extracted via crushing of the tibias, femurs, iliac crests and lumbar vertebrates using mortar and pestle. Subsequently, mouse cells were removed using the Mouse Cell Depletion Kit (Miltenyi Biotec), and genomic DNA was isolated from human cells using the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen). Samples were subjected to targeted sequencing for oncogenic driver mutations using the MSKCC-IMPACT pipeline as previously described  22  . All annotations of amino acid changes inflicted by MEN1 mutations reported in this paper are based on the menin isoform #1 (RefSeq: NM_000244.3). Menin crystals were grown at 21 °C using the sitting drop vapour diffusion method. Purified menin at 11 mg ml -1 in 10 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl and 1 mM tris(2-carboxyethyl)phosphine (TCEP) was pre-incubated with inhibitor compounds dissolved in DMSO. Pre-incubation was done at concentration of 0.6 mM inhibitor. For crystallization, 1.0 μl of the protein-inhibitor complex was mixed with 0.5 μl of seeds and 1.5 μl of a reservoir solution. Revumenib was co-crystallized using as reservoir condition of 0.1 M HEPES pH 7.9, 24% PEG 3350, 0.2 M magnesium nitrate and 20% ethylene glycol. Crystals were flash cooled in cryo protection solution. For data acquisition, the crystal temperature was kept at 100 K. Diffraction data were collected at the Australian Synchrotron (beamline MX2) using a 16 million pixel Dectris Eiger detector. Raw diffraction data were processed and scaled using XDS software (v.18DEC2014). The structures were solved by molecular replacement with MOLREP (v.11.7.03) in CCP4i (v.7.1.018) using the coordinates previously solved structures of menin (Protein Data Bank (PDB) ID: 6PKC) as a search model. The program REFMAC5 (v.5.8.0267) was used for full structure refinement. The refined coordinates of the complex structures have been deposited in the RCSB PDB. The menin-coding sequence was codon optimized and gene synthesis was performed via Twist Bioscience into a bacterial vector system (pTWIST-Amp). Small double-stranded DNA blocks (gblocks; Integrated DNA Technologies) with the MEN1 M327I , MEN1 M327V , MEN1 G331R , MEN1 T349M or MEN1 D136N mutations were synthesized and cloned into pTWIST-Amp-MEN1 using a restriction enzyme-mediated digest (BamHI + HindIII → M327I, M327V, G331R, HindIII + AfeI → T349M, SpeI + ClaI → D136N) and T4-ligase-based cloning approach (all enzymes from New England BioLabs) to insert the mutations into the MEN1-coding sequence. The codons used were: ATG→ATC (for M327I); ATG→GTG (for M327V); GGT→CGT (for G331R); ACC→ATG (for T349M); and GAC→AAC (for D136N). Subsequently, MEN1 was amplified from the generated pTWIST template vectors using the Q5 High-Fidelity 2X Master Mix (New England BioLabs) and primers (forward: 5′-CCCAGGGGCTAGCATGGGTTTGAAAGCGGCGCAGA-3′; reverse: 5′-AGAGGTTGATTGTCGACTTAACGCGTTTATGCATAGTCCGGGACATCA TACGGATAGCCGGCGTAGTCGGGCACGTCGTAGGGGTAAAGTCCCTTCC TTTGTCGTTTCAGAA-3′) under addition of a double-HA tag to the C terminus of menin. The PCR product was gel-purified using the QIAquick Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen) and cloned into the pLEX-puro lentiviral vector system using T4-ligase after digest with NheI and MluI (New England BioLabs). WT human menin was codon optimized for Escherichia coli expression, synthesized and cloned in pET28 + -derived vectors (Twist Biosciences) and the resulting vector was further subcloned with a synthesized gBlock (IDT) to produce a N-terminal StrepII-Avi-TEV menin fusion. Mutant protein plasmids were generated by site-directed mutagenesis using the Q5 Site-Directed Mutagenesis Kit (NEB) following the manufacturer's instructions; all resulting plasmids were sequence verified. Recombinant proteins were expressed as N-terminal StrepII-Avi-TEV fusions in BL21-DE3 Rosetta cells following standard protocols. In brief, each expression was performed at 4-l scale in LB media. Of the overnight starter cultures, 10 ml was added to each litre of LB at 37 °C, and protein expression was induced by addition of 1 mM IPTG at an optical density at 600 nm of 0.6 following change of temperature to 18 °C overnight. The overnight expression cultures were harvested by centrifugation at 4,000g for 20 min and resuspended in buffer containing 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 200 mM NaCl, 2 mM TCEP, 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), 10 μM bestatin, 2 μM E-64, 1 μM pepstatin and 10 μM leupeptin, and lysed by sonication. Following ultracentrifugation, the soluble fraction was passed over Strep-Tactin XT (IBA) affinity resin and eluted with wash buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 200 mM NaCl and 2 mM TCEP) supplemented with 50 mM biotin (MCE). The affinity-purified protein was subject to ion-exchange chromatography (Poros 50HQ) followed by size-exclusion chromatography (Superdex 200 10/300 GL) in 50 mM HEPES pH 7.4, 200 mM NaCl and 2 mM TCEP. The protein-containing fractions were concentrated using ultrafiltration (Millipore) and flash frozen in liquid nitrogen at 10 μM concentration. Menin WT-revumenib. Menin protein at 11 mg ml -1 in 10 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl and 1 mM TCEP was used for setting up crystallization. The menin-revumenib crystal was obtained using cross-seeding from other menin co-crystals. For menin-revumenib crystallization, 1.0 μl of the protein-inhibitor complex was mixed with 0.5 μl of seeds and 1.5 μl of a reservoir solution using the sitting drop vapour diffusion method. The reservoir solution contained 0.1 M HEPES pH 7.9, 24% PEG 3350, 0.2 M magnesium nitrate and 20% ethylene glycol. Crystals were obtained within 10 days of incubation at 21 °C. Menin(M327I)-revumenib. Menin(M327I) protein at 10.7 mg ml -1 in 10 mM Tris pH 7.5, 50 mM NaCl and 1 mM TCEP was used for setting up crystallization. Menin(M327I)-revumenib crystals were obtained using the sitting drop vapour diffusion method with 1 μl of protein-inhibitor mix and 1 μl of reservoir buffer. The reservoir buffer contained 0.1 M MES pH 6.2, 16% PEG 3350, 0.2 M potassium thiocyanate and 20% ethylene glycol. Crystals were obtained within 7 days of incubation at 21 °C. Although most annotations of menin mutations are based on isoform 2, which encodes 610 amino acid residues, some annotations are based on an alternate transcript with 615 amino acids. Biancaniello et al.  23  have proposed that the 615-amino acid isoform be used as the standard reference for menin, which was the reference used to report the crystallography data. References made to the 610-residue isoform in some instances will result in a 5-residue shift in register. The following peptides were synthesized by GenScript: N-terminal FITC-conjugated MLL1 4-43 (C→A) peptide probe (SARWRFPARPGTT GGGGGGGRRGLGGAPRQRVPALLLPPGY) with a C→A modification that improves binding to menin  20  , MLL1 4-43 (C→A) (SARWRFPARPG TTGGGGGGGRRGLGGAPRQRVPALLLPPGY) and MLL1 4-43 (WT) (SCRWRF PARPGTTGGGGGGGRRGLGGAPRQRVPALLLPPGY). N-terminally FITC-labelled and unmodified MLL2 peptides (MLL2 15-48 (SARGRFPG RPRGAGGGGGRGGRGNGAERVRVALR)) were synthesized at GenScript. To derive the FITC-MLL1 4-43 (C→A) peptide K d , the FITC-conjugated MLL1 4-43 (C→A) peptide probe at a final concentration of 1 nM was mixed with increasing concentration of purified StrepII-Avi-TEV-menin (5 μM final top concentration, twofold, 23-point dilution and a buffer control) in an assay buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.5, 200 mM NaCl and 0.1% Pluronic F-68 solution (Sigma)) in 384-well microplates at an assay volume of 15 μl (4514, Corning) and incubated for 30 min at room temperature. For all assays, change in fluorescence polarization was monitored using a PHERAstar FS microplate reader (BMG Labtech). The FITC-conjugated MLL1 4-43 (C→A) peptide K d was obtained from a fit in GraphPad Prism 9 using a one-site total model and averaged from three independent runs with three replicates (n = 3; Extended Data Fig.  4 ). In competitive titration experiments, menin proteins (1 nM WT, 1 nM M327I or 3 nM for T349M) and 1 nM FITC-conjugated MLL1 4-43 (C→A) peptide probe were incubated in an assay buffer for 30 min. Revumenib was then dispensed to a 384-well microplate (4514, Corning) containing 15 μl of the assay mix using D300e Digital Dispenser (HP) and normalized to 1% DMSO followed by 90 min of incubation. The fluorescence polarization was monitored by the PHERAstar FS microplate reader (BMG Labtech). The MLL1 4-43 (WT) and MLL1 4-43 (C→A) peptide titrations were performed by addition of 7.5 μl of twofold 23-point serial dilution into 7.5 μl of assay mix with the final concentrations of 1 nM FITC-conjugated MLL 4-43 peptide probe, 1 nM WT menin or 1 nM menin(M327I) or 3 nM menin(T349M) in assay buffer. The fluorescence polarization was monitored by the PHERAstar FS microplate reader (BMG Labtech). For analysis of the competitive titration experiments, the last 10 cycles of the data were averaged to obtain technical replicates. Data from three independent replicates (n = 3) were plotted and IC 50 values were estimated using the variable slope equation in GraphPad Prism 9. The calculation of K i values was performed using the K i calculator available at  http://websites.umich.edu/~shaomengwanglab/software/ calc_ki/index.html    24  . The assay parameters used for the calculation of K i were: 1 nM probe for all assays, 1 nM WT menin, 1 nM menin(M327I) and 3 nM menin(T349M), with K d (mean ± s.d., n = 3) of 0.76 ± 0.77 nM for WT menin, 0.91 ± 0.99 nM for menin(M327I) and 2.99 ± 1.62 nM for menin(T349M). Off-rates for test compounds were determined using jump dilution experiments in the HTRF assay measuring FITC-MLL 4-43 binding to His-menin. In brief, test compounds (30 nM) were pre-incubated for 1 h with 30 nM His-menin prebound to 30 nM Lanthascreen anti-His-Tb antibodies in 10 μl of menin assay buffer (50 mM Tris pH 7.4, 50 mM NaCl, 5 mM DTT and 0.01% Triton X-100) containing 0.02% fatty acid-free BSA. After pre-incubation, 1 μl of the assay mixture was transferred to 100 μl of menin assay buffer containing 30 nM FITC-MLL 4-43 (1,000× K i ) in white, opaque 384-well plates. The HTRF signal was measured at various times using a 320-nm excitation and 520-nm and 620-nm emission wavelengths with a 50-μs delay and a 200-μs window with the gain set to 2,100 using a BMGlabTech ClarioStar Plus plate reader. The data were normalized to the percent inhibition at each timepoint, in which 0% is the HTRF signal in the presence of 0.3 nM His-menin without test compound, and 100% is the HTRF signal in the absence of His-menin. The resulting percent inhibition values were fit to a one-site exponential dissociation model using XlFit to determine the dissociation rate. All calorimetric experiments were carried out in isothermal titration calorimetry (ITC) buffer (25 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 200 mM NaCl and 1.0 mM TCEP) at 25 °C using an Affinity ITC (TA Instruments) equipped with autosampler. Revumenib was dissolved in DMSO and diluted with the ITC buffer to final concentrations (50-200 μM, 1% DMSO). Protein sample was adjusted to contain 1% DMSO final concentration. The calorimetric cell, containing buffer or menin (10 μM WT menin, 5 μM menin(M327I) or 10 μM menin(T349M)) was titrated by injecting 2.5 μl of revumenib solution with a concentration of 100 μM, 50 μM or 200 μM, respectively, 24 times with the stirring speed at 75 r.p.m. The resulting isotherms were subtracted against buffer runs and fitted with a single-site model to yield thermodynamic parameters of ΔH and ΔS, stoichiometry and K d using NanoAnalyze software (TA Instruments). Cell lines were obtained from the American Type Culture Collection or the Deutsche Sammlung von Mikroorganismen und Zellkulturen and cultured in RPMI-1640 (for MOLM13, MV4;11 and OCI-AML3 cells) or DMEM (for HEK-293T cells) with 10% FBS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin (Life Technologies/Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 37 °C, 5% CO 2 atmosphere and 95% humidity. Cell lines were tested and maintained mycoplasma-negative throughout all experiments. Cell line authentication for MOLM13, MV4;11, and OCI-AML3 cells was performed via short tandem repeat analysis by the MSKCC core facility. For the production of lentivirus, HEK-293T cells were seeded in 10-cm tissue culture-treated dishes (Corning) 24 h before transfection to achieve 80% confluence. pLEX-puro plasmids (5 μg) containing MEN1 WT, MEN1 M327I , MEN1 M327V , MEN1 G331R , MEN1 T349M , MEN1  D136N  or the MEN1 CRISPR-Cas9 base-editor library were transfected along with lentiviral packaging plasmids (2 μg pMD2G and 5 μg psPAX2) using 30 μl XtremeGene9 DNA transfection reagent (Sigma-Millipore) in 1.8 ml Opti-MEM per 10-cm dish containing 4 ml DMEM and 10% FBS (Life Technologies/Thermo Fisher Scientific). Medium was exchanged with 10 ml fresh DMEM and 10% FBS, and viral supernatants were harvested 24 h later by filtering through a 0.45-μm Nalgene syringe filter (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Viral supernatants were frozen at -80 °C or directly used to infect target cells. For lentiviral transduction, target cells were resuspended in crude viral supernatants and spin infection was done in 50-ml Falcon tubes for 2 h at 2,000 r.p.m. in a centrifuge heated to 37 °C. Subsequently, viral supernatants were removed and cells were resuspended in RPMI-1640, 10% FBS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin. Puromycin was added to pLEX-puro-transduced cell lines at a final concentration of 1 μg ml -1 48 h after transduction to select for cells expressing the respective constructs. A single guide RNA (sgRNA) library of 518 sgRNAs targeting all MEN1 exons and flanking untranslated regions (Supplementary Table  2 ) was designed, synthesized and cloned into the pRDA_256 vector system at the Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT via the Genetic Perturbation Platform. Production of lentiviral particles and viral transduction was performed as described above. MOLM13 and MV4;11 cells were transduced with the base-editor library and selected with 1 μg ml -1 puromycin (Thermo Fischer Scientific) for 6 days. After selection, a baseline sample (5 × 10 6 cells) was harvested for DNA extraction and the remaining cells were split into ten separate non-tissue culture-treated T75 culture flasks. Each five of these flasks were treated with 50 nM of VTP-50469 or DMSO as control for 12 days and split every 3 days during this time. At the end of the experiment, cells were harvested and DNA was extracted using the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen). Library construction, next-generation sequencing and generation of an sgRNA count matrix were performed via the Genetic Perturbation Platform at the Broad Institute. β-Scores were calculated for each condition (baseline versus end point) using the MaGECK-MLE pipeline. Differential β-scores for each gRNA were calculated by subtracting the control β-score from the VTP-50469 values. MV4;11 and OCI-AML3 cell lines were passaged 24 h before nucleofection. The gRNA (150 pmol) (sequence: 5′-CATCTACCCCTACATGTACC-3′) was added to Alt-R S.p. HiFi Cas9 nuclease (Integrated DNA Technologies) (125 pmol) followed by incubation at room temperature for 20 min to allow formation of ribonucleoprotein (RNP) complexes. Cells (2 × 10 5 ) were sedimented at 200g for 10 min at room temperature, washed with PBS and resuspended in the SG Cell Line Nucleofector solution (Lonza). Cells, Alt-R Cas9 Electroporation Enhancer (Lonza) (120 pmol) and the HDR donor oligonucleotide containing the MEN1 M327I mutation as well as a silent mutation at the protospacer adjacent motif site (120 pmol) (sequence: 5′-TCCCGCACATTGCGGTTGCGACAGTGGTAGCCAGCGA GGTAGATGTAGGGGTAGATGTGTTCATCCCGATAGTAGGTCTTGGCT-3′) were added to the RNP complex. For WT control, PBS (Gibco, Fisher Scientific) was added to the resuspended cells. Nucleofection was performed using a 16-well 20 μl Nucleocuvette stripe (Lonza) in a 4D-Nucleofector X Unit (Lonza) (program FF-100). Cells were incubated overnight in RPMI-1640, 10% FCS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin containing 1 μM Alt-R HDR Enhancer V2 (Lonza) (or DMSO for WT control). The following day, the medium was replaced by RPMI-1640, 10% FBS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin. Single clones were selec ted in methylcellulose (MethoCult M3234, Stemcell Technologies) supplemented with 10% RPMI-1640, 10% FBS, 1% penicillin-streptomycin and 25 nM revumenib (or DMSO for WT control), starting 3 days after nucleofection, and expanded in RPMI-1640, 10% FCS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin supplemented with 25 nM revumenib (or DMSO for WT control). For the in vitro clonal selection assay of bulk nucleofected cells over time, 5 × 10 3 cells (three replicates per condition) were seeded in RPMI-1640, 10% FBS and 1% penicillin-streptomycin supplemented with 50 nM revumenib (or DMSO for WT control) 3 days after nucleofection. Cells were replated in fresh medium and drug every 3 days, and viable cells were counted using the LSRFortessa (BD Biosciences) flow cytometer. Cumulative cell growth was calculated over 28 days. At each timepoint, cell pellets were frozen and genomic DNA was extracted subsequently using the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen). ddPCR was performed from the genomic DNA to assess editing efficiency in the bulk cells over time. To analyse HDR efficiency in single-cell clones, genomic DNA was PCR-amplified using the Q5 High-Fidelity 2X Master Mix (New England BioLabs) and primers (forward: 5′-CCCTCAGCCCTGCCTTTTCTGC-3′; reverse: 5′-AGTCCTGGACGAGGGTGGTTGG-3′), and the resulting 641-bp fragment containing the Cas9 cut site was gel-purified using the QIAquick Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen). Sanger sequencing was used to analyse HDR efficiency (primer: 5′-CTGGGATCTTCCTGTGGCCCCT-3′). To determine menin inhibitor responses of MOLM13, MV4;11 or OCI-AML3 cell lines expressing MEN1 mutants, 3 × 10 3 cells were plated per well in a non-tissue culture-treated 96-well plate. The menin inhibitors were titrated on these cells in the following dose range: 3.9 nM (for DMSO), 7.813 nM, 15.625 nM, 21.25 nM, 62.5 nM, 125 nM, 250 nM, 500 nM and 1,000 nM. Cells were treated in triplicates on each plate and the experiment was repeated four times. After 6 days, cells were split 1:7 and counts of viable cells in each well were determined after 10 days of treatment by flow cytometry (LSRFortessa with high-throughput sampler, BD Biosciences). Relative cell counts were calculated as the percentage of DMSO control. The average of each triplicate was calculated and the mean of all replicates was plotted. Error bars represent the standard error of the mean. Cells were sequentially crosslinked using 2 mM disuccinimidyl glutarate for 30 min and a final concentration of 1% formaldehyde for 10 min at room temperature (20-25 °C) and stopped with 125 mM glycine. Cells were lysed in lysis buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl at pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCl, 2 mM EDTA, 0.5% NP-40, 1% Triton X-100, 1 mM PMSF and PIC) and incubated on ice for 30 min. The resuspended cells were then dounced in an ice-cold homogenizer. Nuclear pellets were collected and resuspended in shearing buffer (0.1% SDS, 0.5% N-lauroylsarcosine, 1% Triton X-100, 10 mM Tris-HCl at pH 8.1, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM PMSF and PIC). Isolated chromatin was fragmented to an average size of 200-600 bp with a bioruptor (Diagenode). Precleared chromatin was immunoprecipitated overnight at 4 °C (anti-menin, 5 μg per IP; #A300-105A, Lot #11, Bethyl Laboratories; and anti-MLL1, 5 μg per IP; #A300-086A, Lot #7, Bethyl Laboratories) and immunocomplexes were collected with protein A Dynabeads. The immunocomplexes were washed eight times in wash buffer (50 mM HEPES-KOH at pH 7.6, 500 mM LiCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% NP-40, 0.7% sodium deoxycholate, 1 mM PMSF and PIC), followed by two 1× Tris-EDTA washes, and eluted in elution buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl at pH 8.0, 10 mM EDTA and 1% SDS); crosslinks were reversed at 65 °C for 4 h or overnight, and DNA was purified using the DNA Clean and Concentrator Kit according to the manufacturer's instructions. ChIP or input DNA was used for Illumina library construction using the ThruPlex DNA Sequencing kit (Takara) with 12-14 cycles of amplification and the use of single indexing barcodes. Paired-end sequencing (37 bp) was performed on a NextSeq500 platform (Illumina). Raw Illumina NextSeq BCL files were converted to FASTQ using Illumina bcl2fastq. Reads were aligned to the human GRCh38/hg38 genome using STAR 2.7.5. Aligned BAM files were sorted, duplicate reads were marked and removed, and deduplicated BAMs were indexed using Broad picard tools v.2.9.4. Signal intensities around TSSs (±3,000 bp) were quantified using BEDtools (v.2.28.0), and data visualizations were produced using IGVtools (TDF signal pileups; v.2.3.75) and ngs.plot (pileup heatmaps/ torpedo plots). ChIP-seq peaks were called using MACS2 (v.2.1.4.) with appropriate input samples used as controls. Total RNA was isolated from cell lines or mouse cell-depleted PDX material using the RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen). Quality control was performed using RNA-Tape (Agilent), and all samples used for sequencing passed quality control with a RINe-score greater than 8. Poly(A) mRNA enrichment and library preparation were performed using the NEBNext Poly(A) mRNA Magnetic Isolation Module and NEBNext Ultra II RNA Library Prep kit (New England BioLabs) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Sequencing was done on an Illumina NextSeq500 platform as 37-bp paired-end sequencing. Raw Illumina NextSeq BCL files were converted to FASTQ using Illumina bcl2fastq. Reads were aligned to the human GRCh38/hg38 genome using STAR 2.7.5. Aligned BAM files were sorted, duplicate reads were marked and removed, and deduplicated BAMs were indexed using Broad picard tools v.2.9.4. Raw per-gene counts were calculated with HTSeq-count (v.0.6.1pl). Differential RNA sequencing expression was calculated using the BioConductor DESeq2 package (v.1.24,0), using raw unnormalized per-gene counts from deduplicated BAMs. Z-scores for the generation of heatmaps were calculated from regularized gene counts (from DeSeq2 package). Statistics were performed using GraphPad Prism software (GraphPad Software). Statistical analysis of menin inhibitor dose-response differences between MEN1 WT and MEN1-mutant cell lines was performed using the unpaired Student's t-test (two-tailed) (Fig.  3  and Extended Data Figs.  5  and 6 ). The assessment of statistical differences in menin and MLL1 TSS occupancy from ChIP-seq data was performed using the Mann-Whitney U-test (two-tailed), as this data were not normally distributed (Fig.  4  and Extended Data Fig.  7 ). Statistical comparison of disease burden and induction of differentiation in PDX across different conditions was performed using one-way ANOVA (Extended Data Figs.  2  and 3 ). P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant, and significance in the dose-response curves (Fig.  3  and Extended Data Figs.  5  and 6 ) is indicated by: *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01 and ***P &lt; 0.001. Further information on research design is available in the Nature Portfolio Reporting Summary linked to this article.</text><annotation id="12"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="3397" length="8"/><text>Patients</text></annotation><annotation id="13"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="3606" length="7"/><text>Patient</text></annotation><annotation id="14"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="3752" length="7"/><text>patient</text></annotation><annotation id="15"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="3997" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="16"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="4235" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="17"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="4359" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="18"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="4658" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="19"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="4953" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="20"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="5154" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="21"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="5547" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="22"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="5707" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="23"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="5997" length="7"/><text>patient</text></annotation><annotation id="24"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="6044" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="25"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="6348" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="26"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="6446" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="27"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="7580" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="28"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="8419" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="29"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="13399" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="30"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="20123" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="31"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="21325" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="32"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="21473" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="33"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="21512" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="34"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="22038" length="7"/><text>patient</text></annotation><annotation id="35"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="23098" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="36"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="24181" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="37"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="24873" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="38"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="24934" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="39"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="25829" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="40"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="25835" length="12"/><text>participants</text></annotation><annotation id="41"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="26102" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="42"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="26206" length="7"/><text>patient</text></annotation><annotation id="43"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="26298" length="8"/><text>Patients</text></annotation><annotation id="44"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="26744" length="12"/><text>participants</text></annotation><annotation id="45"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="26879" length="7"/><text>Patient</text></annotation><annotation id="46"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="27147" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="47"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="27162" length="12"/><text>participants</text></annotation><annotation id="48"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="27573" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="49"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="27968" length="8"/><text>Patients</text></annotation><annotation id="50"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="28039" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="51"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="28555" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="52"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="28782" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="53"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="28846" length="5"/><text>mouse</text></annotation><annotation id="54"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="28986" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="55"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="29034" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="56"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="29322" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="57"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="29351" length="4"/><text>mice</text></annotation><annotation id="58"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="29834" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="59"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="29947" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="60"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="29991" length="5"/><text>mouse</text></annotation><annotation id="61"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="30093" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="62"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="30353" length="7"/><text>patient</text></annotation><annotation id="63"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="30431" length="8"/><text>patients</text></annotation><annotation id="64"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="30925" length="5"/><text>mouse</text></annotation><annotation id="65"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="30960" length="5"/><text>Mouse</text></annotation><annotation id="66"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="31038" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="67"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="34017" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="68"><infon key="Identifier">*562</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="34053" length="16"/><text>Escherichia coli</text></annotation><annotation id="69"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="51102" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="70"><infon key="Identifier">*10090</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="51644" length="5"/><text>mouse</text></annotation><annotation id="71"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="52286" length="5"/><text>human</text></annotation><annotation id="72"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="8820" length="6"/><text>MOLM13</text></annotation><annotation id="73"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="8842" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="74"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="13890" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="75"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="14119" length="4"/><text>KMT2</text></annotation><annotation id="76"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="14871" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="77"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="14882" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="78"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="15097" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="79"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="15108" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="80"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="15572" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="81"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="16122" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="82"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="16133" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="83"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="18800" length="4"/><text>KMT2</text></annotation><annotation id="84"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="19242" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="85"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="19841" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="86"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="19953" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="87"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="20053" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="88"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="20617" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="89"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="20711" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="90"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="21229" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="91"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="21256" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="92"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="23063" length="4"/><text>KMT2</text></annotation><annotation id="93"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42484" length="6"/><text>MOLM13</text></annotation><annotation id="94"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42492" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="95"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42503" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="96"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42532" length="8"/><text>HEK-293T</text></annotation><annotation id="97"><infon key="Identifier">*9615</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42650" length="4"/><text>CO 2</text></annotation><annotation id="98"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42799" length="6"/><text>MOLM13</text></annotation><annotation id="99"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42807" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="100"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42819" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="101"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="42943" length="8"/><text>HEK-293T</text></annotation><annotation id="102"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="44635" length="6"/><text>MOLM13</text></annotation><annotation id="103"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="44646" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="104"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="45607" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="105"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="45618" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="106"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="48476" length="6"/><text>MOLM13</text></annotation><annotation id="107"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="48484" length="6"/><text>MV4;11</text></annotation><annotation id="108"><infon key="Identifier">*9606</infon><infon key="type">Cell</infon><location offset="48494" length="8"/><text>OCI-AML3</text></annotation><annotation id="109"><infon key="Identifier">*469008</infon><infon key="type">Strain</infon><location offset="34570" length="8"/><text>BL21-DE3</text></annotation></passage></document></collection>